<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="lvr_svg_path">

  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2025 Eduardo Hopperdietzel

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="vector shapes factory">
    This protocol provides an efficient way for clients to define complex shapes.

    One common use for these shapes is masking, as seen in the lvr_background_blur 
    protocol. However, other protocols may apply them for purposes not covered in 
    this document.

    Shapes are expressed as a string of SVG path commands, a standard and widely 
    used format. In the future, this approach may be replaced by separate requests 
    for each type of SVG path command.

    Warning: This protocol is experimental, and backward-incompatible changes may be 
    made in the future.
  </description>

  <interface name="lvr_svg_path_manager" version="1">
    <description summary="SVG path manager">
      This interface allows a compositor to announce support for SVG paths.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the SVG path manager object">
        Destroy the SVG path manager. This doesn't destroy objects created with the 
        manager.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_svg_path">
      <description summary="create a new SVG path object"></description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="lvr_svg_path"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="lvr_svg_path" version="1">
    <description summary="SVG path object">
      The SVG path is described as a string of commands, as outlined here:

      https://svgwg.org/specs/paths/

      After requesting a lvr_svg_path object, the client must send zero or multiple 
      concat_commands if the string exceeds 4096 bytes, which is the default maximum 
      length supported by libwayland. The compositor concatenates the strings in order 
      of receipt. 

      Once all commands are sent, the client must issue a done request, at which point 
      the SVG path is considered complete. Sending a done request without having previously 
      sent a concat_command is valid and represents an empty path. 

      No requests, except for destroy, are accepted after a done event, otherwise, 
      the already_constructed error is emitted.

      Sending a destroy request without having sent a done request triggers the incomplete error. 
      
      If the final string yield an invalid SVG path, the invalid_commands error is emitted. 
      
      The coordinate system of the described path depends on the context in which it is used.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="incomplete" value="0" summary="incomplete svg path"/>
      <entry name="already_constructed" value="1" 
        summary="a request other than destroy was made after a done request"/>
      <entry name="invalid_commands" value="2" 
        summary="the final string doesn't represent a valid svg path"/>
    </enum>
    
    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the vector path object">
      </description>
    </request>
    
    <request name="concat_commands">
      <description summary="append SVG path commands">
        The string size of each request must not exceed the 4096-byte limit.
      </description>
      <arg name="commands" type="string"/>
    </request>
    
    <request name="done">
      <description summary="all commands have been sent">
        Once this request is sent, the only permissible action is destroy.
      </description>
    </request>
    
  </interface>

</protocol>
